Everything in this world can be proven by science.
（中之条 剛(なかのじょうつよし)）この世のものは
すべて科学で証明できるんだ
In the world there are talks about the so-called "spiritual phenomena"...
世間で いろいろ
取り沙汰される霊的現象
There's no way those kinds of sleep-inducing things could be real!
そんな眠たい たぐいの物は
あるはずがない
あってはいけないんだ
It'd be bad if they were.
In other words...
つまり―
霊が信じられないんだ
I don't believe in spirits!
Nichijou 93
I heard that exorcisms were being performed at a local temple, so I went to check it out.
（中之条）近所の寺で除霊を
しているということなので
やってきた
（和尚）…で
どういった ご用件ですかな？
So, what brings you here?
First, I'll pretend I'm possessed by a demon,
（中之条）まずは 悪霊に
取りつかれたことにして
then I'll look for contradictions.
いくつかの矛盾点を
探っていこう
Lately, I've been having the feeling of
something tightening around my throat.
近頃 のどを何者かに―
絞めつけられる感覚に
陥るんですが…
Oh my!
あらま
ほれ これをお使い…
Here.
Use this.
（中之条）きた
Here it comes!
The offering of useless exorcism goods!
どんな根拠のない
除霊グッズを勧める気なんだ
Lozenge
It should work really well on your throat.
（和尚）
のどに効くという代物じゃ
（中之条）ず… ずいぶんと
理にかなってるじゃないか
He's being awfully reasonable.
Is there not enough reality in my story?
僕の話に リアリティーが
足りないだけなのか
とにかく まずは
信じてもらわなければ
Well, then I'll need to get him to believe me.
You see,
いいですか？
it's not just that my throat is sore...
単にのどが痛いのではなく―
その…
It feels like I'm being strangled by someone,
誰かに首を
絞められているというか…
and I think I heard a strange voice.
…かと思うと いきなり
奇声を発したりするらしいです
I'm possessed by something!
ぶっちゃけ
取りつかれたように
Well, isn't it that...
それ あれじゃろ？
...you're just reading too many strange books?
変な本の読みすぎじゃろ？
You shouldn't...
少し… 引くわ
...do that too much...
I never would have thought that someone in the business would tell me that.
（中之条）その言葉を
言われるとは思わなかった
本職に
More importantly, does this priest even believe in spirits?
…というか この住職
本当に霊を信じているのか？
But I came all this way to the temple.
でも せっかく
寺まで来たんだし―
There's no way I'm just going to back down!
このまま のこのこと
帰るわけにはいかない
I'm being strangled by some sort of monster!
恐ろしい者に
なんか しゃにむに―
首を締めつけられてる
ぐううっ
今 はああ…
Excuse me!
（和尚）失礼　プッ
He saw through me!
（中之条）見透かされた
Of course he did.
当たり前だ
I was wrong for trying to fool someone in the business with a half-assed performance!
なまはんかな演技で
本職に たてついた―
僕のほうが悪いんだ
I have to do it seriously.
（中之条）
本意気で示さなければ
To get him to believe,
信じてもらうには
限界まで振り切らねば
I need to go mad!
どああ！
W-What?!
な… なんじゃ！
W-What are you doing?!
（和尚）おい ちょっ 何をする
うわっ ちゃああ！
だあっ だあっ だあっ だあっ
What the heck are you doing?!
何やっとんじゃ お前！
（中之条）ポオオ！
シュッ シュッ ポッ ポッ
What in the world is this?!
き… 貴様！
何じゃ こりゃあ！
おりゃ！
Japanese Martial Arts
（和尚）おわあっ
（中之条）
シュッ シュッ ポッ ポッ
シュッ シュッ
Why you...
（和尚）貴様！
What are you doing...
うちの寺に…
What are you doing to my temple?!
うちの寺に何するんじゃあ！
My dream is to become a scientist.
（中之条）僕の将来の夢は
科学者になることだ
Crap.
（中之条）し… しまった
I seem to have lost myself.
自分を見失いすぎた
To explain everything in this world with science...
この世のすべてを
科学で証明してみせること
...and to help many people understand it.
それを たくさんの人に
理解してもらうこと
And when that time comes, there is one thing I want to express.
そして 時が来たら
一つだけ伝えようと思う
Are you okay?
大丈夫ですか？
Get...
で… 出ていけ この悪霊！
Get out, you demon!
A person can become a demon at any time.
（中之条）人は いつでも
悪霊になれるってね
Nichijou 94
（長野原(ながのはら)よしの）あっ
Gotcha!
隙あり
（立花(たちばな)みほし）
ハッ 誰だ？　んっ
Who is it?!
Mihoshi, it's been a while.
みほし　お久しぶり
Oh, it's Naganohara-san!
出た　長野原さん
I haven't seen you for a while.
しばらく見ないうちに
みほしも中学生になったか
You're already a middle schooler, huh?
Well, lately, you haven't been coming to the dojo at all.
最近 全然
道場 来てないからだろ
I haven't gone to practise at my university lately, either.
最近 大学のほうも
練習行ってないな
I've been skipping!
サボりだ
And yet you still won the National Tournament?
それで このあいだ
全日本優勝かよ
This darn genius type!
（みほし）この天才タイプめ
Are you going to the dojo now?
（よしの）今から道場？
（みほし）そう
Yeah.
Clubs just ended, so I'm going now.
（みほし）
さっき部活終わって これから
Naganohara-san, are you coming?
長野原さん 来るの？
I'm the type that gets weaker when I practise a lot.
私 いっぱい練習すると
弱くなるタイプなんだよね
What is she saying?
（みほし）何 言ってんだ
This darn genius type!
この天才タイプが
（みほし）ハアッ
Although I can accept that she's strong,
（みほし）だけど
確かに強いのは認める
I can't accept that she's strong despite never practising.
納得がいかないのは―
あまり練習してないのに
強いってことなんだ
It's been rumoured that when Naganohara-san was in middle school, she scored a point against the Master!
長野原さんが
中学１年のとき―
師範代相手に
１本取ったという伝説がある
That legendary master!
あの師範代をだ
I'm a middle schooler now, too, but I can't seem to do anything.
同じ中学の私が
全く歯が立たないのに
I go to the dojo after club,
部活のあとに道場に行き
土日 返上して練習してるのに…
and I spend my entire weekend practising.
The Master says that effort will always open up a door!
師範代が言っていた
“努力は必ず扉を開く”
Oh, a black cat!
あっ 黒猫
（みほし）ハアッ
Hey, kitty!
（よしの）おーい　猫さーん
When I look at her, I start to feel uneasy.
（みほし）この人を見てると
ぐらつきそうになる
You're so cute!
（よしの）うわあ カワイイ
I'll take a swing.
（みほし）
一太刀 入れてみたい
Just one.
一太刀
In this situation, even I can...
この状況なら 私でも…
This is the most I can do right now,
今は これしかできないけど
いつか勝負で…
but someday I'll do it in a match.
I'll do it against the Master someday, too!
そして いつか師範代にも…
This darn genius type!
この天才タイプが！
Oh, sorry!
ご… ごめん
ああっ 師範代
Master!
Love-Like
It's cold.
寒っ
Daihuku Fair
Got it?
（中之条さん）
いいか しっかりやるんだぞ
Be sure to do it right.
Reign
Dad intends to pass the business on to me.
（中之条）父さんは僕に
２代目を継がせる気なんだ
Also, take this balloon.
それと この風船
If a kid comes around, hand it to him.
お子様が来たら あげてくれ
I won't stand for this.
（中之条）その手は くわないぞ
隙を見て逃げてやる
As soon as I see a chance, I'm running for it!
But you know...
（中之条）それにしても これ…
This thing...
Daihuku
It isn't floating!
浮いてねえ
Word Of The Day
In the very end, I just want a little bit of a happy ending.
Shinonome Institute
（はかせの
“ジングルベル”のハミング）
A Certain Christmas One-shot
What are you going to ask Santa for, Professor?
（東雲(しののめ)なの）はかせはサンタさんに
何を お願いするんですか？
Well, I want some chocolate,
（はかせ）はかせはね
チョコのやつとね―
色鉛筆とね―
some coloured pencils,
a cake-shaped eraser and...
ケーキの消しゴムとね―
えっと えっと…
Wow!
ああ そんないっぱい
ずるいです
Having that many isn't fair!
Well, what I would like is...
じゃあ じゃあ 私はですね―
Two packs of eggs, 500 grams of beef, a book and...
卵２パックと牛肉500グラムと
イワンビリービンの本と…
（はかせ）はかせが最初に
いっぱい お願いしたんだから―
I've already asked for a lot, so you only get one thing, Nano!
なのは１個だけ！
（はかせ）あっ なの
Nano, if it's only a little more, then I guess it's okay.
えっと えっと…
ちょっとだけ
いっぱいだったら―
大丈夫だから
こ… これも貸してあげるから
I'll let you borrow this, too.
（阪本(さかもと)）ああ…
Bobon!
（サンタ）どうも
Yay, it's Santa!
やった！ サンタだ！
Merry Christma-
メリークリスマス
Delicious Melon Bread
Daihuku
Trap
I'm not sticking around for this!
（中之条）こんな茶番に
つきあってられないよ
I need to hurry up and get this off!
さっさと このお面を脱いで…
（中之条）うえっ 痛い
Ow! It hurts!
痛たたたたた
Are you going to run away, Tsuyoshi?
（中之条さん）逃げる気か 剛
（中之条）父さん
Dad!
I made some modifications to the mask.
（中之条さん）今回は少し
お面に細工をさせてもらった
（中之条）細工？
Modifications?
The inside of that mask...
（中之条さん）
その お面の裏はな―
ペンキ塗りたてだ！
...is freshly coated with glue!
Hot!
（ウェボシー）熱っ！
Damn, I dropped my meat bun!
しまった
速攻 肉まん落とした
I didn't even get to take a bite out of it...
一口も食べてないのに
（フェッちゃん）
まあ まあ ウェボシー
It's fine, Websey!
If there had been poison in that meat bun, you would have died,
もし この肉まんに
毒が入ってたら―
ウェボシー 死んでたんだよ
so it's actually a good thing!
逆に よかったじゃん
No, it isn't!
よかないよ
It's what I look forward to the most on the way home from school...
下校最大の楽しみの一つが
（フェッちゃん）何事もね
You need to always look forward. Your luck will come back.
前向きに生きてれば
ツキは回ってくるもんだよ
Be thankful to the fallen meat bun.
落ちた肉まんに 感謝
Nichijou 95
What's with your extremely positive attitude?
何なの？
そのポジティブキャラは…
I've decided to always be positive, even in tough times!
これからは いかなるときにも
前向きでいこうと決めたんだよ
ほら ほら
Look, if you take off the dirty parts, you can still eat it.
まだ汚れたところ取れば
食べれるじゃん
The poison is already gone?
（ウェボシー）
毒設定 消えるの早いなあ
See? You do it like this-
（フェッちゃん）ほら
こうやって汚れを取ってやれば…
あちっ
Hot!
うおおっ アイス セーフ！
The popsicle is safe!
See?
ほら ほら
前向きな者に訪れる 幸運が
Good things happen when you're positive.
It's positive magic!
イッツ 前向き マジック
My meat bun isn't safe, though...
肉まんがアウトなんだが…
It's times like this you need to be positive!
ほら ほら
こんなときこそ前向きに
If there had been poison in the meat bun,
もし 肉まんに
毒が入ってたら―
you would have died, Websey.
ウェボシー 死んでたよ
バリエーション少ないな
You don't have much variation.
Even if I remove the parts that got dirty,
汚れたところは取るとしても―
I can't accept the fact that some popsicle juice got on it.
アイスが載っかったところが
納得いかん
Come on! Positive thinking-
ほら ほら 前向きに 前向きに
Oh, god!
南無三(なむさん)
さっきの肉まんの熱で
少し緩くなってたか…
The heat from the meat bun must have made it a bit loose.
くう
If I imagine that there was poison in the popsicle, I can handle this...
アイスに毒が入ってたと思えば
これくらい…
You were eating so much of it, though.
（ウェボシー）
バリバリ 食べてたじゃんか
What is it?
どうした？
Loser
Your positiveness just had its combo broken!
コンボで前向き効果
消えたじゃん
No, this is a message from God that I shouldn't eat two because I might get a stomach ache!
いや これは―
“２本食べておなか壊すな”
っていう神からの啓示だよ
おおっ 今日は
フェッちゃんらしからぬ―
That's some Fecchan-like perseverance!
粘りを見せるなあ
Also, if this had been soft serve, it would be completely out.
（フェッちゃん）
しかも このアイス
ソフトクリームだったら
完全にアウトだったけど―
I can just wash off this popsicle.
氷菓子は洗えば
汚れが落ちるからねえ
I'm thankful for that!
そこら辺 感謝
You're still going to eat that?
それ まだ食う気かよ
Wait!
（師範代）待て
（フェッちゃん）あっ
（師範代）ハア ハア　待て
（フェッちゃん）ぐっ… ハア
What's it like?
（フェッちゃん）どんな感じ？
It's like it's wet.
ぬれちゃってる感じ…
Come on, Fecchan!
ほら フェッちゃん
Positive, positive!
ポジティブ ポジティブ
Oh, I give up!
（フェッちゃん）うえーん
もう ギブアップ
Dash for Freedom
If you refuse to inherit my legacy,
（中之条さん）
お前が そうやって２代目を
継がんと言うのなら―
just wait for my second and third traps!
この先 第２ 第３の
ワナを仕掛けるまでだ
Dad...
（中之条）父さん
This...
（中之条）これが…
You...
（中之条さん）お前…
...is my...
（中之条）僕の…
Could it be?!
（中之条さん）まさか…
...answer!
答えだあ！
Guidance Counselling
Tachibana, what are you going to do in the future?
（富岡(とみおか)先生）立花
お前 進路どうするつもりだ？
I'm deciding between going to a university or getting into cooking.
大学に行くか 料理の専門か
迷ってるんですけど…
おお 料理か
Cooking, huh?
Marry him?!
あいつに嫁ぐ？
Calm down, Tachibana.
落ち着け 立花
Shinonome Institute
Tie it like this,
（はかせ）こう縛って
ギュッ
and it's done.
これで よし
I'm back!
ただいま
Oh, Nano, I'm going to take Sakamoto out for a walk.
あっ なの
ちょっと 阪本と散歩してくる
I'm going to have some friends over to study, is that all right?
（なの）
これから友達が来て―
勉強するんですけど
いいですか？
Nichijou 96
（はかせ）分かった
Okay.
はかせも遊ぶから
すぐ帰ってきます
I want to play, too, so I'll be right back.
Well then, I'm off!
じゃあ 行ってきまーす
（なの）はーい
（阪本）あっ ぐっ
おっ ぐうっ くあっ
うっ　お… おい コラ
Hey! What are you doing, kid?!
何やってんだ？ ガキ
I'm going to die!
死ぬ　死ぬ
ぐあっ　おーっと
Okay, I get it.
分かった　望みは聞く
I'll listen to you!
お前の望みは何だ？
What do you want?
（阪本）何が欲しい？
（はかせ）サメ
A shark.
Don't screw around!
（阪本）ふざけんな！
...while crying...
（はかせ）
♪ ひとり泣きながら
（阪本）泣きたいのは俺だ！
I'm the one that wants to cry here!
Okay. A shark.
分かった サメなら お安い ご用だ
Piece of cake!
I'll go get one!
すぐに用意するから
外せ コラー！
Let me off!
（はかせ）うう… 犬だ
Dogs...
They're dogs, so they might bite.
犬だから かまれるかもしれない
Sakamoto, there are dogs.
阪本　犬だ
They might bite us.
かまれるかもしれない
W-What? A-Are you afraid of dogs?
（阪本）
ななな… なに犬なんかに
ビビビビビ… ビビってんだ
T-They're on leads, so there's no way we'll get bitten.
ひひ… ひもついてんだから
かまれるわけないだろう
（はかせ）ギャッ
Our only choice is to run!
こうなったら
逃げるっきゃねえ
All right, run away!
分かった　逃げる
（はかせ･阪本）ギャッ
Sakamoto, we can't escape!
阪本　逃げられない
Don't give up!
（阪本）あきらめるな
If you give up, it's over!
あきらめたら終わりだ
Ask the owner to hurry up and put their leads on!
飼い主に言って
早く ひも つないでもらえ
It's...
もう 終わりだ！
...over!
ダメだ ダメだ
It's no good!
Use your brain!
知恵を ふり絞れ
Isn't there anything?
何かないか？ 何かないか？
I found a gummy in my pocket.
ポケットにグミがあった
（阪本）おっ それだ
That's it!
やつらが食ってるあいだに
逃げるぞ
While they're busy eating it, we'll make our escape!
I know!
（阪本）そうだ
お前は何か逃げる道具 作れ
Make a tool to help us escape.
そうか　忘れてた
Oh, right!
I forgot!
（はかせ）あっ 阪本
（阪本）なんだ？
Sakamoto!
What is it?
I don't have any tools to make a tool!
道具作る道具がない
（阪本）おおっ クソ！
Damn!
Fine then, just do whatever you want!
こうなったら 煮るなり焼くなり
好きにしろ この野郎
TL Note: This is a common Japanese phrase: "Boil me or burn me or do whatever you want to me".
Boil... burn... whatever you want...
Dinner.
（はかせ）
うっ 食べられちゃう
We're going to be eaten.
食べられちゃう
If we're going to be eaten, we might be eaten.
食べられたら
食べられるかもしれない
うわああん
ううっ うわあん
Huh, Professor?
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）あれ？ はかせ
（はかせ）うん？
Why are you crying?
（祐子）
なに泣いてんの？ 迷子？
Are you lost?
（はかせ）ゆっこだ
It's Yukko!
（長野原みお）へえ この子が
前に言ってた“はかせ”か
Oh, this is the Professor you were talking about.
Oh, Sakamoto is with you?
おっ 阪本も一緒
Let me pet him!
（祐子）触らして 触らして
（阪本）うっ
No, Yukko!
違うの ゆっこ 犬やっつけて
Go take care of the dogs!
ひゃあ 思いのほかサラサラしてる
He's a lot softer than I expected!
Me next!
次 私も
Don't screw around!
ふざけないで！
Hurry up and fend the dogs off!
早く 犬やっつけて
（祐子）あっ 分かった
I get it!
かまれたから
敵討ってほしいんでしょう
You want revenge because they bit you!
（はかせ）違うの
これから かまれそうなの
No, they're about to bite us!
アッハッハッハッ 何だ それ
What's that?
さては 犬が怖いんだな
オバＱ(キュー)か
Let me guess: you're scared of dogs? Who are you, Oba-Q?
TL Note: Oba-Q, from the manga Obake no Q-tarou, is deathly afraid of dogs.
違うよ！
That's not it!
だって犬だから かむし
It's a dog, so it's going to bite!
Look how friendly he is.
（祐子）見てみ
There's no way he'll bite.
こんな おとなしいのに
かむわけないじゃん
（はかせ）かむよ
It'll bite.
It won't bite.
かまないよ
It'll bite!
（はかせ）かむー！
Bite some gum?
（祐子）ガムでも かむ？
（みお）えっ
Just kidding.
（祐子）なんつって
It'll bite!
かーむーの！
Well then, look.
（祐子）じゃあ 見ててみ
Here, shake.
（祐子）ほら お手
（オグリキャップ）ガブッ
Hey, Yukko, are you okay?
ちょっと ゆっこ　大丈夫？
It won't bite if you don't get near it, so don't worry.
近づかなければ かまれないから
大丈夫だよ
Yukko was... Yukko was...
ゆっこが… ゆっこが…
（みお）大丈夫
It's okay.
Yukko's just stupid.
ゆっこはバカだから ねっ
I got it.
（はかせ）分かった
All right, let's get Yukko up and go to Nano-chan's house.
（みお）よーし ゆっこ起こして
一緒に なのちゃんち行こうか
（はかせ）
うわあ なの知ってるの？
Oh, you know Nano?
Of course I kn-
（ピョン）ガブッ
（みお）そりゃあ知…
（はかせ）あっ
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）　ハッ
Where were you?!
どこ行ってたの？
You have to keep them on a lead!
ちゃんと ひもしなきゃ
ダメなんだけど！
Did you play with them?
遊んでもらった？
What are you talking about?!
（はかせ）何 言ってんの？
かまれそうなんだけど！
They almost bit us!
（麻衣）あげる
Here.
Chocolate sharks!
サメチョコ
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました
There were dogs, and we got chocolate.
チョコもらったし
犬も行ったし―
Isn't that great, Sakamoto?
よかったね 阪本
（阪本）フンッ
Being afraid of dogs. You're still just a kid.
犬にビビるなんて
まだまだ ガキだな
More importantly, take this rope off of me.
それよか 早く縄取ってくれよ
All right, since I got chocolate.
チョコもらったから いいよ
ううっ　ハア
あれ？
Huh?
What's wrong?
（阪本）どうした？
Sakamoto, take it off.
阪本　取って 固い
It's stuck.
It'd be off already if I could!
（阪本）
取れたら取っとるわい！
Let's get Yukko to take it off.
（はかせ）ゆっこに取ってもらおう
Hey, Yukko, take this off.
ねえ ゆっこ　取って
Hey, Yukko.
ねえ ゆっこ
おっ おおおっ おい
あれって…
Hey!
H-Hey, isn't that...
（阪本･はかせ）
ギャアアアアーッ
うわ ええーん
（はかせ）うえーん
Shinonome Institute
I'm back.
（はかせ）ただいま
There were so many dogs.
犬がいっぱいいた
Wow, you're sweating a lot!
（なの）うわっ
すっごい汗ですね
Oh, right!
あっ そうだ　チョコがあった
There was chocolate!
Chocolate, chocolate, chocolate, chocolate, chocolate...
（はかせ）
♪ チョコ チョコ
...sharks, chocolate, chocolate, chocolate, sharkie, sharkie, sharks...
That being said, Aioi-san and Naganohara-san sure are late.
それにしても
相生さんと長野原さん
遅いなあ
（はかせ）
♪ サメ サメのチョコ
I'm sure they came in this direction...
（きよし）
たしか こっち方面に…
W-What is this?
（きよし）な… なんだ？ これは
Buddy.
バディ
Little Buddy.
コバディ
いったい何やってんだ？
What exactly are they doing?!
あっ おじいちゃん
Grandpa!
People live by helping each other out, Takashi.
（ジェントルマン）
人と人は助け合って
生きるもんじゃ たかし
The same is true about animals' hearts, Takashi.
（ジェントルマン）それは
動物の心も同じじゃ たかし
Don't take the bond between an
animal and a human lightly, Takashi.
（ジェントルマン）動物と
人の絆(きずな)を なめてはいかんぞ
たかし
Grandpa...
おじいちゃん…
I'm Kiyoshi.
きよしだよ
I'm Melon Bread.
Humans, do you prefer it with the taste of melon or without?
Continue the debate over this for eternity.
Next time on Nichijou: Episode 23.
Narration:     Shibata Hidekatsu
Look forward to it!
（メロンパン）メロンパンです
人間どもよ　メロンの味が
したほうがいいのか―
しないほうがいいのか―
永遠に議論を続けるがいい
次回の「日常」は第23話
お楽しみに